but even if someone is not experiencing
low testosterone symptoms and you you
find randomly these low testosterone
levels like 250
300 healthwise wouldn't it be better to
bump those up to 600
700 health reasons defitely would be
cardiovascular benefits for sure yeah
yeah so because we we know that there's
a an association with being hypogonadal
and having an increased risk of serious
cardiovascular events and also um an
increased risk of neurological events
like such as um dementia and Alzheimer's
and things are are associated with so so
yeah I can see the I can see the
argument for it but um I guess that has
to be context specific if you've got a
young male who's yet to have a family
who's 25 and he's an entrepreneur and
he's you know very muscular going to the
gym and he just happens to have bloods
that are 250 300 total T then then you
know you could argue maybe you've got
time to wait for to finish having his
family and things if that's in his plans
um and then look at it again later but
yeah I think it's very context specific
and you need to look at what the actual
picture is with each patient at the
time and and like I said those rible
causes are really really um really
important um and sometimes you w
necessarily know the reversible courses
but they might be the ones that you kind
of want to say let's recheck again in 3
months or six months or whatever as well
um give them the information because
with all of this stuff with um
testosterone deficiency it tends like I
always say if this is a marathon not a
Sprint we don't need to start it off
straight away taking that time to talk
about things if you're in a relationship
as well so that um you know you can talk
it through with them so you can make
those big decisions that you kind of
feel like you're almost being forced
into doing super quickly um but yeah
absolutely s you make a really good
point um if even if you're not
necessarily symptomatic with that
testosterone deficiency it's still worth
considering all the other things that
Felix right pointed out that you can
prevent um even from sort of a metabolic
picture as well sort of metabolic
syndrome um and thinking about again
body composition and uh and fatigue and
mental health as well which is really
important um so if your numbers are low
but you feel okay um you know you might
want to choose to monitor it for a bit
bit and see how things go check out the
reversible courses process and then go
from there that would probably be
something as simple like you
we've seen this before like something as
simple as someone constantly being in a
caloric deficit to maintain a level of
leanness will make them hypogonadal and
as soon as you start eating maintenance
calories SL a little bit more uh your
your testosterone normalizes it's you
know it's sh workers who are doing night
shifts or really long shifts and things
like that it can be a post viral you
know post viruses postco and things it
can really kick around and ditch the
testosterone for quite a long time so
there are so many variables that can
impact it um um and I think the the Bri
Society for sexual medicine recommend at
least two um blood tests sort proving
Low by their standards um
trt um before sorry before providing trt
um and I think that's really really
important because it's a snapshot you
can take it different times of the day
and you'll get different pictures but if
you know somebody if the only bottomy
appointment someone can get is post you
know seven night shifts on the Trot then
actually it it may well be anyway um
yeah he just added I have chronic
insomnia a big belly and osteoporosis I
have an appointment with an
endocrinologist on Tuesday okay yeah I
mean yeah so so so take take the
guidelines with you to speak to that
endocrinologist because um you you know
it's there's not all endocrinologists
created equal is probably a way of
putting that like some people that have
specialist interests in trt will be good
but they if they don't then it may be an
uphill battle but yeah just make sure
you're well
informed yeah they I think they they
seem to run by a different set of
thresholds for treatment so um like I
said we we generally run at Eden clinic
we run through the British Society for
sexual medicine and you can actually
Google their guidelines and they give
you the treatment thresholds for both
free and total testosterone I hope
that's helpful probably when you go the
insurance way they will only look at
numbers and if you're not low enough you
won't get treatment right yeah yeah
that's certainly going to be a factor
for sure if you use health insurance
then um health insurance is are
businesses and they want to make money
rather than give it out